בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף daf is צדי ב tzadi-bet 92.
We're in the middle of the פרק חלק, Perek Chelek, which is
about עולם הבא, Olam Haba, but so many other things as well,
like one of the probably biggest loci, I guess, of אגדתא Agadata
in the גמרא. Gemara.
And before we resume, just a quick mention for the two things
that came up yesterday that both were a bit of a חידוש
chiddush for me. So one, the point about whether רש"י Rashi is
the real רש"י Rashi or not. Apparently, it was Epstein, Y. N.
Epstein, that first raised that question
and thought that it was a תלמיד talmid of רש"י, Rashi, the
ריב"ס, Rivas, whatever, but at least the little research I've done yesterday
seems that based overwhelming, well I don't know, from the scholarship I
read from about 40 years ago, it seemed that there was a
let the overwhelming evidence was that it was רש"י, Rashi, and that
it wasn't somebody else. But anyway, so that's just number one. But
yes, there is some debate, but certainly, I did not get a
sense, although I'm not necessarily one that would have that זכות zchus
reading it, that there was something particularly different than the sort of
normal way that felt different than רש"י. Rashi. Anyway, there is some
of that debate, but at least it seems to me that the
strong evidence is that it is רש"י. Rashi. The other point, which
is that we had a גמרא Gemara yesterday about
ויאפתם תורתכם, Vi-af-tem Toraschem, you have forged your תורה, Torah, I proved
that their תורה Torah was forged, and it did not work so
well in the context of the discussion about מינים, minim, about sectarians,
and Charlie pointed out that the שטיינזלץ, Steinsaltz, whatever the קורן Koren
had, had כותים, Kuthim, Samaritans, which worked very well in context. And
I was a little shocked because normally you have a text that
says מינים, minim, which is censored to read Samaritans, because Samaritans was
not seen
as a loaded word because it wasn't relating to anybody. There are
some still some Samaritans around, but in the context of the Jews
of the Middle Ages, it wasn't seen as relating to any relevant
people. But I actually looked at the manuscripts. You can get all
the גמרא Gemara manuscripts online. It's amazing. Anyway, and I actually looked,
all the manuscripts have כותים, Kuthim, have Samaritans. So presumably, that was
the original text. It makes total sense in context. I have no
idea how come it was thought that the word Samaritans had to
get somehow changed or censored to מינים. minim. I really don't know.
Maybe somebody thought that it was a censorship and they tried to
switch it back or something. Very strange. Okay, let's continue. We're now
in the middle of debate between רבי Rabbi and אנטונינוס, Antoninus, and
I'd actually be curious who they think. Do they think אנטונינוס Antoninus
is like Marcus Aurelius? They think it is. Okay, so they built
a friendship. Okay.
So that's interesting. At least according to the גמרא Gemara they did.
Right, how much this is historical is an interesting question. But anyway,
so obviously we're getting off. It started with some topics
about asking about the body and the soul and how God, how
each one of them God can judge, since each one can say
it wasn't my fault, and it says God puts them back and
then judges them together, and that very much fits with the idea
that the יום הדין Yom Hadin here is after the period of
resurrection when body and souls are resurrected. And we raised the whole
question of that whole body-soul dualism, which is surprisingly actually more originally
a Greek idea than it is a Jewish one, although obviously very
pervasive by the time we get to the Talmudic period. Okay, anyway,
but now we continue. So if we pick up, which is right
exactly, ואמר ליה אנטונינוס לרבי, Ve-amar lei Antoninus le-Rabbi,
so the line starts with the word רבי, Rabbi, and it is
about 13 lines before the lines get wide on צדי א עמוד
ב. tzadi-alef amud-bet. אמר ליה אנטונינוס לרבי נשמה משעת נתנה באדם. Amar
lei Antoninus le-Rabbi neshama misha'as nitna ba-adam.
So again, going back to this נשמה neshama and גוף, guf, so
when is the soul, when does the soul become embodied, or want
to say the other way, when does the body become ensouled?
Okay? So משעת פקידה או משעת יצירה, mish'at pekida o mish'at yetzira,
from the time of conception or from the time of formation. The
idea is
that the fetus doesn't get formed, doesn't start developing a form until
40 days after conception. So at what stage does it enter into
the body? By the way, we just had in this בראשית, Bereishis,
it says נפש חיה nefesh chaya is described as the animals. But
does that mean this body-soul dualism, or does נפש חיה nefesh chaya
just mean that it has the animated spirit, that
it's
alive? Although that's by animals. God ויפח באפיו נשמת חיים, vayipach be'apav
nishmat chayim, right, so on the one hand it says ויהי האדם
לנפש חיה. vayehi ha'adam lenefesh chaya. That's not really different than the
word I think that well, what is it used by the animals?
It says נשמת nishmat and here it says נפש. nefesh. So I
think there's a difference between נשמה neshama מעיקרא דפשיטא m'ika d'pashat that
it says by the animals, and נפש nefesh that it says by
the אדם. adam. נפש nefesh means וינפש, vayinafesh, that God was like
the breath of God. So it's actually interesting, the word for soul,
although נשימה neshima is also breath. But anyway, okay, it's not exactly
clear in the story there. You know, both says that it's a
soul of life, so animals have life and humans have life, right?
Because in the water it's too, המים שרץ נפש. hamayim sheretz nefesh.
Oh, it does have נפש חיה. nefesh chaya. And then by the
and by the human it says ויהי האדם לנפש חיה, vayehi ha'adam
lenefesh chaya, right?
So נפש חיה. nefesh chaya.
Right. נפש חיה למינה, nefesh chaya lemina, right? So there's not a
big diff- so it's actually the exact same term, but the human
beings have God breathing the breath of life into the humans, right?
So anyway, so again, getting to that question, you know, not to
overdo this Greek versus Hebrew sense of, you know, of the body-soul
dualism, clearly there is something from God that is being breathed into.
And here you want to know, when is the נשמה neshama placed
in the body?
Does this have any
philosophical,
does this have any practical-
well we're going to get- I'll get to that. Okay. משעת פקידה
misha'as pekida או משעת יצירה, o misha'as yetzira, from the time of
conception or the time of formation? אמר ליה משעת יצירה, amar lei
mish'at yetzira, from the time of formation, you know, it's nothing like
the גמרא Gemara calls it מיא, maya, it's water before that, only
once it starts having some human form. Forty days. Yes, okay. אמר
ליה, amar lei, so אנטונינוס Antoninus said back to him, אפשר חתיכת
בשר עומדת שלושה ימים בלא מלח ואינה מסרחת? efshar chatichat basar omedet
shlosha yamim belo melach ve'eina masracha? How can you have that? That
means that for forty days, I mean again, it doesn't say forty
days but everybody reads that into here. How can you say for
forty days it's standing there without anything to preserve it? If you
had a piece of raw meat unrefrigerated, with you know, without salt
for three days, it would start to spoil. So if you have
a soul in it that gives it life, okay, that prevents it
from spoiling, but how do you have forty days of development? Why
doesn't the, you know, why doesn't the meat
spoil inside the inside the womb? אלא משעת פקידה, ela mish'at pekida,
it must be from the moment of conception. אמר רבי דבר זה
למדני אנטונינוס. amar Rabbi davar ze limadani Antoninus. I learned this from
Antoninus. ומקרא מסייעו, umikra mesaye'o, he's right. No, he made a good
logical argument. It wasn't like I had a מסורה mesora about this.
And actually, he has a- once I realized that he was right,
I found a verse that supports him, שנאמר ופקודתך שמרה רוחי, shenemar
upkudat'cha shamra ruchi,
your visitation guarded my spirit. Okay, so from the moment of פקידה
pekida that God- and that's also the פסוק pasuk right? וה' פקד
את שרה, v'Hashem pakad et Sarah, right? The moment that God visitation,
meaning of of conception, the spirit is you know, you God have
preserved my spirit. Actually I think the מהרש"א Maharsha also reads it
that the spirit has guarded my my flesh, meaning the presence of
the spirit in the fetus protects the flesh already from the moment
of of conception. Now Michael said, okay, this is all very interesting
philosophical, does it have any practical ramifications? So some people want to
sort of make an argument from this, you know, oh, well, then
maybe issues about abortion, right, should start from the moment that the
soul enters into the body, and maybe should there should be abortion
issues even less than forty days, even from the you know, even
from the day moment of conception, which is I by the way
I believe a Christian belief, right, that it all starts from the
moment of conception where when does life begin.
So I can only tell you that I don't again, I can't
tell you with definitivity that nobody makes that argument, but our- but
that argument is basically dismissed, like because it's not- this is not
a legal discussion. And the idea that somehow the halachic status of
somebody as a as a person as a partial person, I mean
the- it's always potential life, right? So but when does it get
beyond potential life to be something of more legal standing? Okay, now
I you know, so there just- most all of the discussions about
abortion deal with much more halachic גמרות. Gemarot. Now if we didn't
have as much halachic גמרות Gemarot about abortion, I wouldn't be surprised
if people would go to this. You know, sometimes in contemporary medical,
halachic medical issues, like you know, maternity and paternity by artificial
insemination and surrogate motherhood and so on, there's like no גמרות, Gemarot,
so people turn to אגדתות. aggadot. Okay, so if you didn't have
real halachic גמרות, Gemarot, I wouldn't be surprised if people turned to
this. But because of the presence of halachic גמרות, Gemarot, those פוסקים
poskim basically say, you know, this is just a philosophical discussion, it's
not about the legal standing. Okay, which I understand. Some people say,
how could you say this? The soul is in the is in
the flesh, obviously you know, that should have some halachic significance. Why
doesn't it? I mean- yeah, so I don't know. Again, let's also
remember that are we talking here about the soul in terms of
the distinctively, if we want to use this terminology, human, you know,
צלם אלוקים tzelem Elokim divine soul? Or are we talking about maybe
you know, maybe talking about the נפש חיה? nefesh chaya? Maybe you
could ask the same question about when an animal, when does the
soul of an animal enter its body? How does the flesh of
an animal when it's developing in the cow's womb, how does that
not spoil, right? So it's not necessarily that נשמה. neshama. Okay, although
earlier the נשמה neshama was more sort of the the you know,
the humanness, the choice, you know, the בחירה bechira and so on.
All right, moving on though. But yes, obviously it's a suggestive גמרא.
Gemara. Okay. Now, where
were we? Okay. ואמר ליה אנטונינוס לרבי, ve'amar lei Antoninus le'Rabbi, Antoninus
said to Rabbi, מאמתי יצר הרע שולט באדם? me'eimatai yeitzer hara sholet
ba'adam? Now, now, when does the evil inclination start having an impact
on the human, right, having control over the human person, the human?
משעת יצירה? mish'at yetzira? And this is presumably something that's not in
the soul of animals although you don't know, sometimes the יצר... yeitzer...
Sometimes the יצר הרע yeitzer hara is conceptualized as the sort of
animalistic drives, right? So anyway, but okay, from the time of conception,
או משעת יציאה, o mishat yetzia, or from the time it exits?
Right, I'd assume that it was not simply sort of maybe eliminated
already at the time of formation. So now we're looking at either
when the soul enters in, comes with the יצר הרע, yeitzer hara,
or maybe when it starts getting out into the wide world, right,
and so is born. So I don't know why, I know it
could have, but I don't know why. Who knows? Yeah, who knows.
אמר ליה משעת יצירה, amar lei mishat yetzira, from the time of
formation, okay. I'm sorry, I'm sorry, oh it's not משעת פקידה, mishat
pekida, משעת יצירה, mishat yetzira, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I should have
shown Sanhedrin, צ"א, Tzadik Aleph, צ"א. Tzadik Aleph. מאימתי יצר הרע, me-eimatai
yeitzer hara, maybe there's יצר, yeitzer, יצירה. yetzira.
Notice that both words יצר, yeitzer,
יצירה, yetzira, יציאה, yetzia, I don't know if that's just by chance.
מאימתי יצר הרע שולט באדם, me-eimatai yeitzer hara sholeit ba-adam, משעת יצירה
mishat yetzira from the time it's formed, okay, או משעת יציאה o
mishat yetzia from the time it exits. Right, I don't know why
it doesn't have the possibility of משעת פקידה. mishat pekida. אמר ליה
משעת יצירה, amar lei mishat yetzira, from the time it's formed. Rabbi
keeps on going back to the time of formation, that's when it
starts becoming human. אמר ליה אם כן בועט במעי אמו ויוצא. amar
lei im kein boeit be-mei imo ve-yotzei. If that's true, it would
start trying to get out from the time it was, you know,
already in the mother's womb.
Why doesn't it leave the womb?
I don't know, well, I'm not sure יצר הרע yeitzer hara necessarily
means an evil drive, it could mean an evil drive, it might
just more mean like drives, you know? It's like sort of like,
you know, so if it has sort of like its, you know,
and babies, right, I, whatever, I think it could, I don't think
it necessarily means like the most evil sense of the יצר הרע.
yeitzer hara. I think it just means, you know, desire, right? It's
so if, you know, the so it's drives and it's desires and
so on. So if it had those when it was still in
the womb, it wouldn't be, it wouldn't be accepting of its state
in the womb. Like that's, you know, it would start pushing and
kicking. Of course, you have some women, of course, they feel like,
you know, that's exactly what the baby was doing for the whole
nine months, you know, kicking and trying to get out and so
on, feeling anyway. But yes, but it's, but it's more like I
think if you think about it more as like, you know, animalistic
drives. Again, animalistic has a negative connotation, but drives in general. Okay,
so then why is it placid and staying in the womb and
not complaining? So, אלא משעת יציאה, ela mishat yetzia, it must be
from the time it exits. אמר רבי דבר זה למדני אנטונינוס ומקרא
מסייעו, amar Rabbi davar zeh limadani Antoninus u-mikra mesayeio, Rabbi said, Antoninus
taught me this and the verse supports it, שנאמר לפתח חטאת רובץ,
shene-emar l'fetach chatat roveitz, sin crouches by the doorway, and it's understanding
the doorway here as the opening of the womb. When you exit
the womb, right? Of course, you know, of course if you look
at רש"י Rashi by the פסוק כי יצר לב האדם רע מנעוריו,
pasuk ki yeitzer leiv ha-adam ra mi-ne'urav, which we just happened, right?
רש"י Rashi says,
oh right, that's נח, Noach, right, right. I'm sorry. Anyway, so רש"י
Rashi says משעה שננער לצאת, mi-sha-ah she-nina'ar latzeit, right? What does רש"י
Rashi say there? לא אוסיף עוד לקלל את האדמה בעבור האדם כי
יצר לב האדם רע מנעוריו. lo osif od l'kaleil et ha-adamah ba'avur
ha-adam ki yeitzer leiv ha-adam ra mi-ne'urav. Where was it? Right, נח,
Noach, אוסיף עוד. osif od.
Right, I know, I know. רע מנעוריו, ra mi-ne'urav, מנעוריו כתיב משננער
לצאת ממעי אמו נתן בו יצר הרע, mi-ne'urav ktiv mi-shenina'ar latzeit mi-mei
imo natan bo yeitzer hara, according to
בראשית רבה. Bereishit Rabbah.
So that's not exactly when it actually exited but when it started
getting ready to exit. I guess that's because it's pushing its way
out, so that makes sense, you know, the side of יצר הרע.
yeitzer hara. It's like it's, it's got its drives, it's, you know,
it's, it's asserting itself. So that's from the time that it's exiting.
Of course, you know, we also know the whole מדרשים midrashim about
יעקב ועשו, Yaakov ve-Esav, right? That he would pass by the בית
עבודה זרה beit avodah zarah and עשו Esav would be trying to
kick and come out. So it's a little inconsistent about all of
that. The מהרש"א Maharsha discusses some of that. Okay. אמר רבי דבר
זה, amar Rabbi davar zeh,
we just did that. ריש לקיש רמי, Reish Lakish rami, Reish Lakish
pointed to a contradiction. כתיב, ktiv, one verse says בם עור ופסח
הרה ויולדת יחדו. bam iver u-fisei'ach harah ve-yoledet yachdav. So now we're
back to עולם הבא. Olam Ha-ba. Okay. So one verse says there's
the blind and the lame who shall be pregnant and give birth
together. Okay. וכתיב, u-ktiv, and another verse says אז ידלג
כאיל פסח, az yidaleig ka-ayal pisei'ach, then the lame will leap like
a, like an איל, ayal, doe, not a doe, what is it?
איל, ayal, right? איל. ayal. Yes, it's a doe,
or a hart. A hart, a hart, whatever that is. Okay, it's
some type of a deer, right? ותרון לשון אלם, ve-taron leshon ileim,
and the language of the mute will sing forth. Okay. כי נבקעו
במדבר מים ונחלים בערבה, ki nivke'u ba-midbar mayim u-nechalim ba-aravah, like in
the desert will burst forth water and in the wadis, right, will
be whatever, you know, will be like lush land. So what's so,
the problem is aren't people back to this thing that, you know,
רמב"ם Rambam didn't like at all, like the questions about do they
come up from the dead with or without their clothes? So here's
the question about when they rise from the dead, when there's תחיית
המתים, tchiyat ha-meitim, will they rise healed or will they rise and
then they're with all of their, you know, people's like limitations? Okay.
So here it says when it says הרה ויולדת יחדו, harah ve-yoledet
yachdav, it sounds like the birthing will be, the way it's being
read, they'll be birthed, meaning they'll be reborn with being עור ופסח,
iver u-fisei'ach, those
that... the lame will be will run and the mute will sing
forth. So הא כיצד? ha keitzad? But remember the רמב"ם Rambam shouldn't
be doing it, why is the גמרא Gemara doing it?
Because the גמרא Gemara didn't agree with the רמב"ם, Rambam, okay. הא
כיצד? ha keitzad? How is this possible? עומדים במומם ומתרפאין. omdim bemumam
umitrapin. So they'll be resurrected with their blemishes and then they'll be
healed. Okay, so you could philosophize about why that will be important,
right? Is it just to prevent another
miracle, to show that they're the same people that they were when
they were resurrected? I don't know. Okay, עולא רמי. Ula rami. עולא
Ula showed a contradiction. כתיב, ktiv, one verse says, בלע המות לנצח
ומחה ה' דמעה מעל כל פנים, bila hamavet lanetzach umacha Hashem dima
me'al kol panim, that's a פסוק pasuk that's quoted a lot at
funerals, right? That in the future time death will completely be destroyed
and God will wipe out the tears from all faces. So it
sounds like there will be no death in the future world. Okay,
וכתיב u'chtiv in another פסוק pasuk says כי הנער בן מאה שנה
ימות ki hana'ar ben me'ah shanah yamut that at the age of
a hundred if somebody dies that'll be they'll say they died in
their young age. But okay, so the life-time will be expanded but
still it won't be that there won't be death at all. לא
יהיה משם עוד עול ימים. lo yihyeh misham od ul yamim. There
will no longer be a burden of days because people will live
to such a long life. לא קשיא. lo kashya. So how do
you reconcile this? כאן בישראל כאן בעובדי כוכבים. kan be'Yisrael kan be'ovdei
kochavim. The difference is Jews versus non-Jews. Okay, so Jews will, now
again what are we talking about, right? So
the general assumption here is that there's a תחיית המתים techiyat hametim
and after the תחיית המתים techiyat hametim there'll be an עולם הבא.
olam haba. The עולם הבא olam haba like I said might be
an embodied עולם הבא, olam haba, but could be an embodied עולם
הבא olam haba with no death, right? So you have the body
but there's no eating and no drinking and no death and so
on, okay. Very much against רמב"ם's Rambam idea that there's a תחיית
המתים techiyat hametim and then they'll die, etc. In this future time
there'll be no death, except the non-Jews they will die. Okay, by
the way another interesting question, right? In the future time when we
imagine, right, ובאו כל האובדים מארץ אשור u'vau kol ha'ovdim me'eretz ashur
whatever it is, no not that one. כי ביתי בית תפילה יקרא
לכל העמים ki beiti beit tefillah yikarei lechol ha'amim and everybody will
recognize God etc. So there's interesting questions. Does that mean, how do
we envision the non-Jews at that time, right? So do we envision
it that the vision in the פסוקים pesukim that they'll all recognize
God? So do we mean first of all does that mean that
they will will they maintain a distinction between Jews and non-Jews in
עולם הבא? olam haba? Maybe everybody will recognize the true faith and
therefore there won't be any distinction.
If they recognized God, would we have them not recognize each other?
Mostly בני נח? bnei Noach? Oh so that's another question. So another
question is that is that will there everybody become Jewish? Or here's
another possibility. There's an opinion that מצוות בטלות לעתיד לבוא. mitzvot betelot
le'atid lavo. The whole purpose of מצוות mitzvot were to get us
into, with our current human limitations and the imperfections of the human
nature and of the world nowadays, we need those מצוות. mitzvot. But
maybe לעתיד לבוא le'atid lavo there's no purpose for it. There's an
opinion מצוות בטלות לעתיד לבוא. mitzvot betelot le'atid lavo. So if מצוות
mitzvot are בטלות לעתיד לבוא, betelot le'atid lavo, maybe there'll be no
difference between Jews and non-Jews, not because all the non-Jews will become
Jews, but because there won't be any sort of, you know, religious
particularism at all. It'll just be everybody just believes in God and
sits and just connects to God and so all those things that
distinguish. So there's three possibilities about how we envision this, assuming we
envision the non-Jews in the world to come, which is what the
גמרא's Gemara about to talk about. Okay, one is that it'll maintain
the difference between Jews and non-Jews. The non-Jews will still be non-Jews
but they'll recognize God, but they'll still have their distinctive practices. Or
everybody will become Jewish. Or everybody will become some very generic type
of a religion because we won't need מצוות לעתיד לבוא. mitzvot le'atid
lavo. Anyway, so here the גמרא Gemara imagines the non-Jews in the
world to come, but says there will be a distinction and they,
but they won't live forever, only Jews will live forever. They'll live
for hundreds of years but not forever. So now the גמרא Gemara
says, ועובדי כוכבים מאי בעו התם? ve'ovdei kochavim mai ba'u hatam? Who
invited the non-Jews? What are the non-Jews doing there? So this is
obviously presaging an important discussion that's going to be in the גמרא
Gemara where they חסידי אומות העולם יש להם חלק לעולם הבא. chasidei
umot ha'olam yesh lahem chelek le'olam haba. Will righteous non-Jews have a
portion in the world to come? Okay, again the simple sense of
the פסוקים pesukim certainly is certainly when it imagines Messianic times, as
I said, כי ביתי בית תפילה יקרא לכל העמים. ki beiti beit
tefillah yikarei lechol ha'amim. Maybe Messianic times is different from עולם הבא,
olam haba, right, remember because Messianic times is okay, there's תחיית המתים
techiyat hametim etc., but the world hasn't transformed. So maybe the transformation
of עולם הבא, olam haba, maybe that but anyway, okay, but but
the פסוקים pesukim certainly imagine non-Jews at least in Messianic times. Anyway,
so the גמרא Gemara says what are the non-Jews doing there? So
מאי בעו התם? mai ba'u hatam? So הנך דכתיב בהו ועמדו זרים
ורעו צאנכם ובני נכר אכריכם וכורמיכם. hanach dechtiv behu ve'amdu zarim vera'u
tzonchem uvenei nechar ikareichem vechormeichem.
Oh no, we're going to need them to be our workers. It
says that the foreigners will come and they'll watch your sheep and
they'll be your farmers and tend your vineyards. So that's why we
need them for. Not because they merit it, but just we need
people to do our work for us. Okay, so this is obviously
going to be an ongoing interesting theme about the role of non-Jews
whether they're present and what their role is etc. And also like
I said, thinking about the possible difference between ימות המשיח yemot hamashiach
and עולם הבא. olam haba. Okay. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
says like this. רב חסדא רמי. Rav Chisda rami. רב חסדא Rav
Chisda Okay, okay, so now the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says like this,
רב חסדא רמי *Rav Chisda rami*, רב חסדא *Rav Chisda* showed a
contradiction. כתיב *Ksav*, one verse says, וחפרה הלבנה ובושה החמה כי מלך
ה' צבאות *Vechafra halevana uvesha hachama ki malach Hashem tzevaot*. Okay, one
says that the moon will be embarrassed, will be shamed, and the
sun will be embarrassed because God will be king. So the light
of the moon and the sun will be garnished, right? Because in
the presence of the divine splendor. So they'll be embarrassed from their
own light. וכתיב *Vekisiv*, so that's again all understood to be in
the future time. וכתיב *Vekisiv*, another verse says, ויהי אור הלבנה כאור
החמה ואור החמה יהיה שבעתים כאור שבעת הימים *Vayhi or halevana ke-or
hachama ve-or hachama yihye shivatayim ke-or shivat yamayim*. The sun of the
light... the light of the moon will be like the light of
the sun, and the sun of the light... the light of the
sun will be seven times, you know, like the original seven days
of creation. Anyway, it sounds like there'll be tremendous light and it
will be powerful, it will be meaningful. So are we going to
have an increased light of the sun and the moon or is
it just going to be God's glow, light is going to overwhelm
them? לא קשיא Lo kashya. כאן לימות המשיח כאן לעולם הבא le'olam
haba. *Lo kashya, kan li-yemos hamashiach kan le-olam haba*. The difference is
in Messianic times and עולם הבא Olam HaBa. *Olam Haba*. In Messianic
times, the light of the sun and the moon will be that
much greater. Okay, whereas in... I don't know, is that supposed to
be global warming or something? Anyway, and in עולם הבא Olam HaBa,
*Olam Haba*, okay, that's when is... you know, that's when it'll all
just be God, right? We might not even be existing, living in
this type... it won't be this type of a physical existence at
all. So it'll all just be God's, you know, the light coming
from God will overwhelm. Right, right, there you go. ושמואל *u-Shmuel*, finally,
now we're introducing שמואל *Shmuel*, דאמר אין בין העולם הזה לימות המשיח
אלא Ela שעבוד גלויות בלבד *de-amar ein bein olam hazeh li-yemos hamashiach
ela shibud galuyos bilvad*. I think Rambam's version is שעבוד מלכויות בלבד
*shibud malchuyos bilvad*. Anyway, there's no difference between this world and the
Messianic times except whether we remain under the subjugation of foreign nations
or in exile. Okay, it's not going to be a miraculous time,
Messianic times. So in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, this is always just
a single opinion of שמואל *Shmuel*. I've already said that Rambam quotes
it and makes it as if this is the consensus of the
rabbis. אמרו חכמים *Ameru chachamim*, says the Rambam, אין בין העולם הזה
לימות המשיח *ein bein olam hazeh li-yemos hamashiach*. Okay, but anyway, in
the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara*, it's very much a single opinion of שמואל
*Shmuel*. So according to him, how do you reconcile the verses? לא
קשיא כאן במחנה צדיקים tzadikkim כאן במחנה שכינה *Lo kashya, kan bi-machaneh
tzadikim kan bi-machaneh shechina*. If you're in the camp of the righteous,
right, of the concept borrows from the idea of the, you know,
in the מדבר *midbar*, right? You had the מחנה שכינה *machaneh shechina*,
which was the משכן *Mishkan*, and then you had, you know, the
camp immediately around it, and then the further, the twelve tribes around
that. So if you're right there in the center, right with God,
then God's glow, you know, shining will overwhelm the glow of the
sun and the moon etc. While you're a little bit more distant,
you'll have the strength and shining of the sun and the moon.
Okay, רבא רמי *Rava rami*. Because even though, because the point being
that even for שמואל *Shmuel*, who says that there's not going to
be any difference with מחנה שכינה *machaneh shechina*, I should point, excuse
me, with what do you call it, with ימות המשיח *Yemos HaMashiach*,
he obviously doesn't deny a transformed world in עולם הבא olam haba.
*Olam Haba*. Right, we should point that out. Right, שמואל *Shmuel* is
just saying Messianic times are going to be this-worldly. שמואל *Shmuel* is
not denying, right, a, you know, an עולם הבא olam haba, *Olam
Haba*, which is going to be
otherworldly. Alright, everybody get that point? Because even שמואל *Shmuel* right says
that oh no, you know, okay, so both of these verses are
עולם הבא olam haba, *Olam Haba*. The sun being seven times and
the sun being embarrassed. It's just different places or different locate... whatever
in עולם הבא olam haba. *Olam Haba*. So עולם הבא olam haba.
*Olam Haba* will be miraculous, it's just Messianic times will not. Okay,
moving on. Now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this. Where were
we? רבא רמי *Rava rami*. Rava shows a contradiction. כתיב *Ksav*, one
verse says, אני אמית ואחיה *Ani amis ve-achayeh*. I will kill and
bring to life. וכתיב *Vekisiv* in another verse says, also just from
the שמחת תורה Torah. *Simchas Torah* there, מחצתי ואני ארפא *machatzti va-ani
erpa*. I will... right,
I will wound and I will heal. So I don't understand, if
you're, you know, if what's the contradiction? I think the contradiction, I
don't even know what the contradiction is.
What you know, if you're going to kill them, I mean, you
know, what's ארפא *erpa* I guess.
I mean, I guess, מחצתי ואני ארפא *machatzti va-ani erpa*... what's the
order of the פסוק pasuk *pasuk*? מחצתי ואני ארפא *machatzti va-ani erpa*,
אני אמית ואחיה *ani amis ve-achayeh*. Which means the words are מחצתי
ואני ארפא ואין מידי מציל *machatzti va-ani erpa ve-ein mi-yadi matzil*. Right.
So if you're bringing to life, why do you have to heal?
אמר הקדוש ברוך הוא *Amar Kadosh Baruch Hu*, מה שאני ממית אני
מחיה *mah she-ani meimis, ani mechayeh*. Because look, first I'll bring the
dead to life, והדר *va-hadar* מה שאני מחצתי ואני ארפא *mah she-machatzti
va-ani erpa*. And then I will, right, exactly what we had before,
right, exactly. That after they are brought back to life, then they
are healed. Fine. תנו רבנן *Tanu rabanan*, אני אמית ואחיה *ani amis
ve-achayeh*. Now we're going to use this as a source to prove
תחיית המתים מן התורה techiyat hameitim min HaTorah, *techiyas hamaysim min ha-Torah*.
אני אמית ואחיה *ani amis ve-achayeh*. יכול שתהא מיתה באחד וחיים באחד
*Yachol she-tehei misa be-echad ve-chayim be-echad*, maybe it means one person dies
and another person comes to life, כדרך העולם ליהוי *ke-derech ha-olam lohe*?
That's the normal way of the world. תלמוד לומר *Talmud lomar*, מחצתי
ואני ארפא *machatzti va-ani erpa*. No, you can learn from the second
part of the verse. I wound and I heal. מה מחיצה ורפואה
באחד *Mah mechitza u-refuah be-echad*, the same way healing is on the
same person that the wound occurred, that's what it means to be
healed, person has a wound, אף מיתה וחיים באחד *af misa ve-chayim
be-echad*. So when it says I bring death and bring life, it
means the life I'm going to bring is to the person who
died. So that's the basis for תחיית המתים techiyat hameitim, *techiyas hamaysim*.
Okay, מכאן תשובה לאומרים אין תחיית המתים מן התורה techiyat hameitim min
HaTorah. *mikan teshuvah la-omrim ein techiyas hamaysim min ha-Torah*. Here's a response
to those who say there's no resurrection of the dead from the
Torah. Here's a response to those that say that's not based in
the verse. Clearly by the parallel of the verse when God says
I bring to life it means I bring those that are already
dead to life. תניא. Why didn't they use?
I don't know.
I'm on אמר רבי מאיר. Amar Rabbi Meir. מניין? Minalan? We're going
back to that theme, okay? You're right, we had a whole תחיית
המתים tchiyat hametim. מן התורה, we got onto other topics, imagining different
aspects of עולם הבא. olam haba. Now we're back to תחיית המתים
tchiyat hametim מן התורה. אמר רבי מאיר: Amar Rabbi Meir: מניין לתחיית
המתים מן התורה? Minalan l'techiyat hameitim min HaTorah? שנאמר: She'ne'emar: אז ישיר
משה ובני ישראל את השירה הזאת לה'. Az yashir Moshe u'vnei Yisrael
et hashira hazot l'Hashem. שר לא
נאמר—he Shar lo ne'emar sang—אלא ישיר—will ela yashir sing.
Of course, obviously it's just a poetic form of using future in
the place of past, but anyway, מכאן לתחיית המתים מן התורה. mikan
l'techiyat hameitim min HaTorah. Here's a base source for it. כיוצא בדבר
אתה אומר: Kayozei vadavar ata omer: אז יבנה יהושע מזבח לה'. Az
yivneh Yehoshua mizbe'ach l'Hashem. בנה לא נאמר—he Bana lo ne'emar built—אלא יבנה—will
ela yivneh build. מכאן לתחיית המתים מן התורה. Mikan l'techiyat hameitim min
HaTorah. אלא מעתה, Ela me'ata, says
the גמרא, Gemara those are all nice פסוקים pesukim to imagine in
the future that Moshe will sing praise God and Yehoshua will build
an altar. But how about this? אז יבנה שלמה במה לכמוש שקוץ
מואב. Az yivneh Shlomo bama l'Chemoshe shikutz Moav. Shlomo
will build an altar for Chemosh, the idol of Moav. הכי נמי
דיבנה? Hachi nami d'yivneh?
So Shlomo's going to be resurrected in order that he can be
עובד עבודה זרה oved avoda zara in the future?
אלא—no, what does the י' yud mean? מעלה עליו הכתוב כאילו בנה.
Ma'aleh alav hakatuv k'ilu bana. No, there the י' yud means he
wanted to build and therefore we're going to consider it as if
he built, so we're also sort of saving Shlomo's honor a little
bit there by that future tense. So there the future tense means
that he desired to. Okay, but we know that's not true by
Moshe. Moshe actually sang the song. So the future tense by Moshe
means that he will do it again in the future.
Okay. לגבי עבודה זרה Legabei avoda zara we don't—no, it's the opposite.
דוקא Davka by עבודה זרה avoda zara we consider the intent as
if you did it. Okay, but by Moshe it means that he'll
do it again in the future. Okay. אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי:
Amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi: מניין לתחיית המתים מן התורה? Minalan l'techiyat
hameitim min HaTorah? שנאמר: She'ne'emar: אשרי יושבי ביתך עוד יהללוך סלה. Ashrei
yoshvei veitecha, od yehalelucha sela. Praised are those who live in your
house, they will
once again praise you forever. 'Sela' is the just word for the
word 'sela', forever. היללוך לא נאמר—they Hilulucha lo ne'emar have praised you—אלא
יהללוך—will ela yehalelucha praise you. מכאן לתחיית המתים מן התורה. Mikan l'techiyat
hameitim min HaTorah. אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי, Amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben
Levi, similarly: כל האומר שירה בעולם הזה זוכה ואומרה לעולם הבא. Kol
ha'omer shira ba'olam hazeh, zocheh v'omra l'Olam HaBa. If you sing out
God's praises in this world, you will merit to sing them out
in the world to come. שנאמר: She'ne'emar: אשרי יושבי ביתך עוד יהללוך
סלה. Ashrei yoshvei veitecha, od yehalelucha sela. Those that dwell in God's
house now—you could have said כל העוסק בתורה, kol ha'osek baTorah, right?
יושבי ביתך—you Yoshvei veitecha could have learned to mean like dwelling in—but
no, here it's reading it in the context of the second half
of the verse: if you're in God's house, like maybe בית כנסת
beit knesset or whatever and you're praising God, you will praise God
in the future. אמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן: Amar
Rabbi Chiyya bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan: מניין לתחיית המתים מן התורה?
Minalan l'techiyat hameitim min HaTorah? שנאמר: She'ne'emar: קול צופיך נשאו קול יחדיו
ירננו. Kol tzofayich nas'u kol yachdav yeranenu.
The sound of your visionaries lifted up their voice together and they
sang forth. ריננו לא נאמר—it Rinnenu lo ne'emar doesn't say they sang
forth in the past—אלא ירננו—they ela yeranenu will sing forth. מכאן לתחיית
המתים מן התורה. Mikan l'techiyat hameitim min HaTorah. We're getting a theme
here.
Okay, but in the process of bringing all this evidence, it also
starts to draw a nice picture of עולם הבא, Olam HaBa of
תחיית המתים, tchiyat hametim that all the dead will be resurrected and
they'll be all praising God and singing. So it sort of is
a little more colorful in terms of that. ואמר רבי חייא בר
אבא אמר רבי יוחנן: V'amar Rabbi Chiyya bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan:
עתידין כל הנביאים כולם אומרים שירה בקול אחד. Atidin kol hanevi'im kulam
omerim shira bekol echad. All the prophets in the future will all
sing שירה shira in one voice, they'll all be a wonderful harmony.
שנאמר: She'ne'emar: קול צופיך נשאו קול יחדיו ירננו. Kol tzofayich nas'u kol
yachdav yeranenu.
They will all sing forth together. One wonders if that's going back
to the גמרא Gemara we learned before of סגנון אחד. signon echad.
Exactly, that different prophets have a same vision but they articulate it
in their own distinctive styles. So maybe here it's sort of saying
in the future times their perception of God will all be so
clear that they'll all articulate it sort of in the same voice,
it won't be sort of as subjective.
אמר רבי יהודה אמר
רב:
Amar
Rabbi Yehuda amar Rav: כל
המונע הלכה מפי תלמיד כאילו גוזלו מנחלת אבותיו. Kol hamone'a halacha mipi
talmid k'ilu gozlo minachalat avotav. Anybody holds back a—this, because this is
the same—whoever holds back
a הלכה halacha from a student is like you're stealing them from
their patrimony, from their ancestral inheritance.
I
was also looking for the word patrimony. Anyway, שנאמר, she'ne'emar, maybe we'll
see the tie-in later. שנאמר, She'ne'emar, as it
says: תורה צוה לנו משה מורשה קהלת יעקב. Torah tziva lanu Moshe
morasha kehilat Yaakov.
It is
an inheritance, a bequest. So therefore מורשה היא לכל ישראל מששת ימי
בראשית. morasha hi l'chol Yisrael misheshet yemei bereishit. It is our national
inheritance and therefore we cannot deny it to anybody.
So, does it explain there why it's being brought in?
אמר רב חנא בר ביזנא אמר רבי שמעון חסידא. Amar Rav Chana
bar Bizna amar Rabbi Shimon Chasida. כל המונע הלכה מפי תלמיד, kol
hamonei'a halacha mi-pi talmid,
anybody who holds back
a הלכה halacha from a student, says, oh you know I can't
teach you, whatever, אפילו עוברין שבמעי אמא מקללין אותו: afilu ubarin she-be-mei
imma mekalelin oto:
even the fetuses in the mother's womb curse him out. שנאמר: shenemar:
מונע בר יקבהו
לאום. moneia bar yikvuhu le'om. One who holds back a sustenance or
grain will be cursed by the nations. ואין לאום אלא עוברין, ve-ein
le'om ela ubarin, and לאום le'om means the fetuses. שנאמר: shenemar: ולאום
מלאום יאמץ. u-le'om mi-le'om ye'ematz. Okay,
one nation will strive against another, by יעקב Yaakov and עשו. Esav.
ואין קבו אלא קללה, ve-ein kovo ela klala, and to קבו kovo
means to curse. שנאמר: shenemar: מה אקוב לא קבה אל. mah ekov
lo kavo el. ואין בר, ve-ein bar, and grain, אלא תורה, ela
Torah, is תורה. Torah. שנאמר: shenemar: נשקו בר פן יאנף. nashku bar
pen ye'enaf. Okay.
So anyway, so and עולא אמר... Ulla amar... what about the תלמיד
talmid though?
How do we get a תלמיד talmid in?
I don't know. עולא בר שמואל אמר: Ulla bar Shmuel amar: מנקבין
אותו ככברה. menakvin oto ke-khivara. They will, they will pierce him like
a sieve. Somebody who holds back will deserve to be pierced through
like a sieve. כתיב הכא יקבהו לאום, ktiv hacha yikvuhu le'om, or
לאום, le'om, I guess לאום. le'om. וכתיב התם ויקב חור בדלתו u-ktiv
hatam vayikov chor be-dalto to make, to, so יקוב yikov doesn't just
mean to curse, it means to pierce through. Okay, so, so, ואביי
אמר: ve-Abaye amar: כאוכלא דקצרי. ke-ukhla de-katzrei.
It will be like the, like the, type of a, what do
you call it, like a sieve or whatever, a sprinkler used
by
the launderers. So that, you know, they use to sprinkle water or
whatever on the clothes, so it's something that's filled with holes. Okay,
so
it'd be impressive, right? I guess.
But it's an interesting image because if you're trying to hold inside,
so they're being
pierced so everything they're trying to keep to themselves... oh that's a
nice point. Everything they're trying to keep to themselves, they get, you
know, they lose what they have. כתיב הכא יקבהו לאום וכתיב התם...
ktiv hacha yikvuhu le'om u-ktiv hatam... oh I just did that. ואם
למדו מה שכרו? ve-im limdo mah s'charo? If you choose to teach
somebody, what is your reward? אמר רבא אמר רב ששת: amar Rava
amar Rav Sheshet: זוכה לברכות כיוסף. zokhe le-vrakhot ke-Yosef. You merit blessings
like יוסף. Yosef. שנאמר: shenemar: וברכה לראש משביר. u-vrakha le-rosh mashbir. But
the blessing's to the head of the one who provides sustenance. ואין
משביר אלא יוסף, ve-ein mashbir ela Yosef, and the משביר mashbir is
יוסף. Yosef. שנאמר: shenemar: יוסף הוא השליט על הארץ הוא המשביר לכל
עם הארץ. Yosef hu ha-shalit al ha-aretz hu ha-mashbir le-khol am ha-aretz.
And he provided for his whole family and therefore you will equally
be provided for. Now I don't know exactly what the tie-in here
is to what we said before, but I do want to say
something beautiful that the מהרש"א Maharsha points out, right? Because this obviously
speaks very much to me, you know. I mean, I have two
boys who are on the spectrum and it was always and it's
whatever, it was a, not just a challenge. We were not able
to find for them a good, an appropriate education in the Jewish
schools. And that is, you know, a real issue, particularly, you know,
with some kids, who are, are we as a community making the
right efforts we need to in order to make sure that every
child is entitled to a Jewish education and to really see that
through? So the מהרש"א Maharsha on this גמרא, Gemara I'll just read
you one line about it where he says the following. He says,
what does he say? כל המונע הלכה מפי תלמיד כאילו גוזלו מנחלת
אבותיו. kol ha-moneia halacha mi-pi talmid ke-ilu gozlo mi-nachalat avotav. מצותה לומר,
mitzvatah lomar, what does this mean that you're stealing, that you're not
teaching somebody? Doesn't just mean like oh you're just being dismissive. שאינו
לומד עם התלמיד כרב פרידא שהיה למוד עם תלמידו ד' מאות פעמים
עד שהיתה שגורה לו בפה. she-eino lomed im ha-talmid ke-Rav Preida she-haya
lamud im talmido arba me'ot pe'amim ad she-hayta shegurah lo ba-peh. He
says, it means that you don't extend yourself like the גמרא Gemara
tells you about רב פרידא Rav Preida that he would learn 400
times with a student who wasn't getting it until he was able
to learn. So it doesn't just mean like pfh I'm not going
to teach. It means you, no, you'll teach the easy students and
you won't teach the students that require a lot of effort. וזה
שאמר המונע הלכה מפי תלמידו, ve-zeh she-amar ha-moneia halacha mi-pi talmido,
from the mouth of the תלמיד. talmid. לומדים אותו עד שתהא שגורה
לו בפה, lomdim oto ad she-te-hei shegurah lo ba-peh, that you have
to teach until the תלמיד talmid is able to really have it
fluent. ופי שאומר הרב שאין התלמיד הגון, u-fi she-omer ha-rav she-ein ha-talmid
hagun, because the rabbi says, psh I'm not, you know, I'll teach
students that are, that are worthy, but this student, he's not so
smart, he's not so worthy, he's not, so it's not worth my
time. וראוי לכך ואי אפשר לו ללמדו, ve-ra'ui le-khakh ve-i efshar lo
le-lamdo, I can't teach him, he's not teachable. הרי גוזלו מנחלת אבותיו.
harei gozlo mi-nachalat avotav. You, this, you steal him from the inheritance
of the fathers, you know, from our national sort of inheritance. שהתורה
היא מורשה לכל ישראל מששת ימי בראשית. she-ha-Torah hi morasha le-khol Yisrael
mi-sheshet yemei bereshit. ורצה לומר, ve-ratza lomar, and then הוא לפי בריאותם
וטבעם מששת ימי בראשית מוכנים כל ישראל ללמוד תורה. hu le-fi beri'utam
ve-tiv'am mi-sheshet yemei bereshit mukhanim kol Yisrael lilmod Torah. We all have
the ability and the right to be learning תורה. Torah. And then
he also speaks about, you know, the idea that even the fetuses
curse out, because the idea that even the fetuses in the womb
have learned all of תורה. Torah. So they, you know, so we
all have this sort of right and this capacity and, you know,
to, and connection to תורה. Torah And to feel that oh I'm
not going to bother to, you know, do it if it's too
hard, right, so that's if, this גמרא Gemara, really spoke very powerfully
to me in terms of that. Again, I don't know exactly what
the connection is to what we were just saying. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר רב ששת: amar Rav Sheshet:
כל המלמד תורה בעולם הזה, kol ha-melamed Torah ba-olam ha-zeh, maybe it
was to, to get a lead-in to this point. That could have
been. Whoever teaches תורה Torah, in this world, זוכה ומלמדה לעולם הבא,
zokhe u-melamdah le-olam ha-ba, will merit and teach it in the world
to come. שנאמר: shenemar: ומרוה גם הוא יורה. u-marveh gam hu yoreh.
I think it's ומרוה. u-marveh. Anyway,
so the one who satiates, it might be picking up before teaching
talking about Torah like it was like rain or like it was
sustenance, but it could also be read here ומורה umoreh to teach,
right? ומרוה, umarve, you mean like rain? Right,
right, right. He will also teach. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, מניין לתחיית
המתים מן התורה? minayin litchiyat hametim min HaTorah? Back to תחיית המתים.
tchiyat hametim. שנאמר, Shene'emar, יחי ראובן ואל ימות, yechi Reuven veal yamot,
let Reuven live and not die. יחי ראובן Yechi Reuven בעולם הזה
ba'olam hazeh ואל ימות veal yamot לעולם הבא. Then double language sort
of like the reverse of הכרת תכרת, hikaret tikaret, you know, הכרת
בעולם הזה hikaret ba'olam hazeh תכרת בעולם הבא. tikaret ba'olam haba. So
here in the positive, will live and not die, live in this
world and not die in the world to come.
Which again connects the תחיית המתים tchiyat hametim. to the...
Oh, that's a good point, although right, right, maybe the יחי yechi
because Reuven was already dead when משה Moshe was saying this. So
you're right, יחי ראובן yechi Reuven might be the תחיית המתים tchiyat
hametim, and then the עולם הבא. olam haba רבינא אמר מהכא. Ravina
amar me'hacha. And
רבינא, Ravina, finally it took the גמרא Gemara two דפים dappim I
think, right, or a דף daf and a half to get to
this פסוק pasuk in דניאל, Daniel, which is the most explicit פסוק
pasuk. in all of תנ״ך Tanakh about תחיית המתים. Techiyas Hamisim. Okay,
and here's the פסוק. pasuk Because other things sort of envision Messianic
time, but this פסוק pasuk. really it talks about תחיית המתים. techiyas
hameisim, שנאמר, Shene'emar, ורבים מישני אדמת עפר יקיצו, verabim miyshenei admat afar
yakitzu,
many of those that are sleeping in the dust will wake up.
אלה לחיי עולם, ele lechayei olam, these for go, some
for eternal life, ואלה לחרפות ולדראון ve'ele lacharafot ulediraon and others to
shame and to whatever, perdition. Okay, so it's explicit. This verse here,
there'll be תחיית המתים, techiyas hameisim, some will, then there'll be a
day of judgment implicitly, some will get עולם הבא, olam haba and
some will go back to גיהנום. Gehennom. All in these like six
words in the פסוק.
pasuk Okay, so some people whatever have a hard time with this.
Yeah, he says it's all a משל. mashal.
You know, but also here it seems
it's ורבים, verabim, not everybody. I don't know what to tell you.
Okay. רב אשי אמר מהכא. Rav Ashi amar me'hacha. Anyway, it's so
funny the גמרא Gemara, just drops this in the middle of everything
else. The point is, is that this פסוק pasuk is like one
of the latest פסוקים pesukim in תנ״ך. Tanakh. So, you know, you
want to actually try to source it earlier because you don't... this
is what the רמב״ם Rambam dealt with in his מאמר תחיית המתים.
Ma'amar Techiat Hametim. You don't want to say, oh this was a
later development, right? So therefore that's I assume why the גמרא, Gemara
you know, only drops this in way in the middle and much
later in the conversation.
What about the valley of the dry
bones?
We're going to get to that. Dry bones. Okay. You know, it's
a funny comic. Okay, let's go. Okay, so. רב אשי אמר מהכא,
Rav Ashi amar me'hacha, ואתה לך לקץ, ve'ata lech lakeitz, you go
for the end of the time, this is also in the פסוק
pasuk, in דניאל, Daniel, ותנוח, vetanuach, meaning you will die, ותנוח ותעמד
לגורלך, vetanuach veta'amod legoralcha,
and then you'll be put to rest and then in the end
you will stand up for your ultimate fate. לקץ הימין lekeitz hayamin
to the end of days. There's a whole, there's a whole interesting
sort of
cabbalistic issue, is it לקץ הימין lekeitz hayamin or לקץ הימים? lekeitz
hayamim? Is it the end of God's right hand or is it
the end of days, right? So anyway.
Like in פרשת נצבים, Parshat Nitzavim, you know like the ספרדים Sephardim
versus אשכנזים Ashkenazim and ימים yamim versus ימין. yamin.
I know, I know, but this is not grammar. They make something
up of this grammar. אמר רבי אלעזר, Amar Rabbi Elazar, כל פרנס
שמנהיג את הציבור בנחת, kol parnas shemanhig et hatzibur benachat, זוכה ומנהיגם
לעולם הבא. zocheh umanhigam le'olam haba. So now we're back to, if
you act well in this world, you will get to... the point
is not just you'll be rewarded. You notice that the theme is,
that the things that you excelled in in this world, you will
continue to do in עולם הבא, olam haba? you'll merit to do
them in עולם הבא. olam haba Which by the way, for רמב״ם
Rambam who does read this as a metaphor, you know, the way,
you know, you could sort of say this is, the more you
actualize your soul in a particular way, is it in learning תורה,
Torah is it in praising God, is it in leadership, then that
will be the dimension of your soul that will continue to exist
even after your, even after you die, right? So there is a,
not just a sense that you'll be rewarded, but this will be
what you continue to be doing in עולם הבא. Okay, so it
says why? שנאמר, Shene'emar, כי מרחמם ינהגם, ki merachamam yenahagem, the one
who have compassion on them, that's you lead them בנחת. benachat. Okay,
you lead them, you don't, you know, you don't just sort of
use your authority and throw it around and do to have a
harsh leadership, you have a pleasant leadership. ועל מבועי מים ינהלם, ve'al
mabu'ei mayim yenahalem,
will lead them by the wellsprings of water. So presumably the wellsprings
of water is also like an image of like the עולם הבא.
ואמר רבי אלעזר, Ve'amar Rabbi Elazar, גדולה דעה שניתנה בין שתי אותיות.
gedolah de'ah shenitnah bein shtei otiyot. So since he quoted רבי אלעזר
Rabbi Elazar here, we'll quote רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar here, the only
connection presumably is it's the same
רבי אלעזר. Rabbi Elazar. Great is knowledge, that or intellect, that it
appears between literally two letters, but it also means between two of
God's names,
okay. שנאמר, Shene'emar, כי אל דעות ה׳, ki El de'ot Hashem, God
is a God of knowledge, of intellect. Now does it just mean
it's between two of God's names, or the way the מהרש״א Maharsha
emphasizes is that it also sort of represents a sense of מידת
הדין middat hadin and מידת הרחמים, middat harachamim, because אל El is
God's מידת הדין middat hadin and דעות de'ot is מידת הרחמים, middat
harachamim, and you know, maybe it also speaks about the complex aspect.
to truly understand something where right maybe also a little bit going
back on the previous point about leading people בנחת. BeNachat. When is
it possible, when is it right to be using דין, Din, when
is it right to be using רחמים, Rachamim, right that sort of
sense of, you know, of wisdom and understanding, okay, you know, it
requires great, you know, great understanding. So דעה, De'ah, the proper knowledge
about how to act and when to act and so on, and
to truly understand things and do the proper thing, that is a
very great quality and it represents, you know, these two sides, this
divine nature, and according to the מהרש"א Maharsha again, this מידת הדין
Midat HaDin and מידת הרחמים. Midat HaRachamim. Then Rabbi Elazar, גדול מקדש
שניתן בין שתי אותיות. Gadol Mikdash shenitan bein shtei otiyot. The בית
המקדש Beit HaMikdash was given between two of God's names, שנאמר פעלת
השם מקדש השם כוננו ידיך. Shene'emar Pa'alta Hashem Mikdash Hashem konenu yadecha.
You have fashioned God, the sanctuary of God, you have your hands
have created. Now, there it sounds like it's the same name of
God, but if you look in the פסוקים, Pesukim, the first השם
Hashem is אדני Alef Dalet Nun Yud and the second one is
יהוה, Yud Ke Vav Ke, so it could also be a מידת
הדין Midat HaDin and מידת הרחמים Midat HaRachamim type of an idea.
And the מהרש"א Maharsha also points out that the גמרא Gemara says
that בצלאל Bezalel knew how to be מצרף Metzaref the אותיות, Otiyot,
again playing on the word אותיות, Otiyot, the letters of God's name,
and made through that he made the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. So
it's a nice tie-in, the דעת, Da'at, knowledge, and the letters and
the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, right? So if you have if you
truly understand things and you have these powers to this divine power
to tap into the divine and ultimately to create the בית המקדש,
Beit HaMikdash, that's a nice way of sort of wrapping all of
that together. Okay. מתקיף לה רב אדא, Matkif lah Rav Adda, Rav
Adda asked him that. קרחינאה, Karchinaos, that was his name, Rav Adda
Karchinaos. אלא מעתה גדולה נקמה שניתנה בין שתי אותיות. Ela me'ata gedola
nekama shenitna bein shtei otiyot. Okay, so then vengeance also should be
great because it appears it was given between two of God's names,
שנאמר אל נקמות השם אל נקמות הופיע. Shene'emar Kel nekamot Hashem Kel
nekamot hofi'a. Again, notice again though the two different names of God,
right? So so do we all go around trying to be zealous
and vengeful? So אל
נקמות הופיע. Kel nekamot hofi'a. אמר ליה למילתה הכי נמי. Amar lei
lemilta hachi nami. Yeah, when it's appropriate to use that מידה, Midah,
then it is a good, it is divine, and maybe again that's
the מידת הדין Midat HaDin and מידת הרחמים, Midat HaRachamim, right? Maybe
except for when it comes to vengeance, מידת הרחמים Midat HaRachamim should
be telling you that you that it's almost never proper, but there
are some times where where it is proper.
Okay. כדאמר עולא Ke'd'amar Ulla right,
פנחס Pinchas and the whole פנחס Pinchas issue. You know, one of
the things we haven't been doing the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, but I actually
wanted to mention that the ירושלמי Yerushalmi said about פנחס, Pinchas, it
says that the sages at that time actually wanted to put him
in חרם. Cherem. So and then it said that but then the
divine voice came out and said הנני נותן לו את בריתי שלום.
Hineni noten lo et briti shalom. You know, so it was even
more explicit than our גמרא that wanted that it was a that
it was not something that we should actually condone, you know. Anyway,
but you know, maybe there are ways in which a very limited
way in which it's appropriate. דאמר עולא, De'amar Ulla, שתי הופעיות הללו
למה? Shtei hofa'ayot halalu lama? Why does it say אל נקמות הופיע,
Kel nekamot hofi'a, right, why does it or why does it say
two נקמות Nekamot or two demonstrations of God's vengeance? אחת למידה טובה
ואחת למידת פורענות. Achat lemida tova ve'achat lemidat pur'anut. One for one
for reward and one for for punishment. Now where is the reward
is not exactly clear. You know, רש"י Rashi says הופיע מהר פארן,
Hofi'a meHar Paran, it's like God sort of punished the non-Jews by,
you know, the whole story that they refused the תורה Torah and
therefore revealed the תורה Torah to בני ישראל. Bnei Yisrael. So it's
not actually the מידה Midah of נקמה Nekama to בני ישראל. Bnei
Yisrael. So anyway, it's not exactly clear how that connects to נקמה
Nekama directly. Anyway. ואמר רבי אלעזר כל אדם שיש לו דעה כאילו
נבנה בית המקדש בימיו, Ve'amar Rabbi Elazar kol adam sheyesh lo de'ah
ke'ilu nivneh Beit HaMikdash beyamav, back to דעה. De'ah. Anybody who has
intellect, again tying in the דעה De'ah with the בית המקדש, Beit
HaMikdash, שזה ניתן בין שתי אותיות וזה ניתן בין שתי אותיות. Shezeh
nitan bein shtei otiyot vezeh nitan bein shtei otiyot. Okay, so explicitly
connecting those two. Which is also a way of saying that, you
know, that because this is a divine quality you don't necessarily need
the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash as a way of connecting to God,
right? If you're able to develop your mind and understanding or whatever,
you know, and it's also like how תורה Torah, winds up sort
of replacing the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, right? So therefore, right, exactly.
Okay. ואמר רבי אלעזר כל אדם שיש לו דעה לסוף מתעשר. Ve'amar
Rabbi Elazar kol adam sheyesh lo de'ah lesof mitasher. By the way,
this works very well with רמב"ם Rambam because for רמב"ם Rambam the
whole reason you get עולם הבא is because you developed your intellect
to understand God, right? So the whole focus here on the intellect
or whatever. Anyway. ואמר רבי אלעזר כל אדם שיש לו דעה לסוף
מתעשר. Ve'amar Rabbi Elazar kol adam sheyesh lo de'ah lesof mitasher. In
the end will become rich. שנאמר ובדעת חדרים ימלאו. Shene'emar U've'da'at chadarim
yimale'u.
With with knowledge your your rooms will be filled, כל הון יקר
ונעים, Kol hon yakar vena'im, with all pleasant types of treasure. Okay,
so of course that could be literal, right, if you're very smart
you know how to invest in the stock market, but it could
also mean that like you know the things that are you know
you know the things that are worth having, right, figuratively, right, you
know you'll have you know that you know you'll live a very
rich rich life. Okay. ואמר רבי אלעזר כל אדם שאין בו דעה
אסור לרחם עליו. Ve'amar Rabbi Elazar kol adam she'ein bo de'ah assur
lerachem alav. You can't have compassion on him, שנאמר כי לא עם
בינות הוא. Shene'emar Ki lo am binot hu. They are not a
nation of understanding, על כן לא ירחמנו עושהו. Al ken lo yerachamenu
osehu. Therefore their their creator will not have compassion on them, ויצרו
לא יחוננו. Veyotzro lo yechunenu. And their fashioner will not have compassion.
a kindness to them. Now, does that really mean somebody who isn't
born with it? Presumably what he means is somebody who doesn't use
or develop their intellect, somebody who's making choices, right, and saying like,
I'd rather just spend all my time sitting and watching TV rather
than trying to whatever, and then they get themselves into trouble. Now,
does he also literally mean that? You know, okay, somebody acted stupid.
Like, so you're not supposed to try to help them out? I
mean, you know, it raises very interesting and challenging questions. I mean,
look, if somebody actually tries, you know, to hurt themselves or whatever,
you know, commit suicide God forbid, you're still מחלל שבת mechallel Shabbat
to save their lives. You don't say that they don't, you know,
have lost their right to to, you know, to be protected, etc.
Okay, so it raises interesting questions over like, okay, but where should
we be like investing our resources? For people who use them well,
you know, or people who are, you know, who aren't, you know,
who are just going to take the money and throw it away.
So, you know, I don't know, it's an interesting it raises interesting
and important questions about that. Okay.
ואמר רבי אלעזר, V'amar Rabbi Elazar, כל הנותן פיתו למי שאין בו
דעה, kol ha'noten pito le'mi she'ein bo de'ah, יסורין באין עליו. yissurin
ba'in alav. So if you give your bread to somebody who has
no intellect, you'll be punished. שנאמר, she'ne'emar, לחמך ישים מזור תחתיך אין
תבונה. lachmecha yasim mazor tachtecha ein tevunah. Your bread will be placed
as a מזור, mazor, probably a healing underneath you or whatever, we'll
see what מזור mazor means, there is no understanding. ואין מזור אלא
יסורין, ve'ein mazor ela yissurin, מזור mazor actually means affliction. שנאמר, she'ne'emar,
וירא אפרים את חליו ויהודה את מזורו. vayar Efraim et cholyo vihuda
et mazoro. Okay, so therefore if you give your bread then you
will get afflictions in a case of אין תבונה ein tevunah when
you gave it to someone who had no understanding. Again, I would
rather I would at least like to read this as somebody who's
like squandered opportunities, is choosing not to develop their intellect, is acting
in a stupid way. I mean, even then, it's it's difficult, but
like if somebody
who's an enabler and keeps giving drugs to
a right, oh, that's interesting. Right, right, by keeping on and supporting
them, you're just encouraging them. Right. Maybe it gets back to the
whole also issue about about the מידת הדין midat hadin ומידת הרחמים.
umidat harachamim. Sometimes people need some tough love, right? You know, you
don't start just, you know, supporting them. Like you said, don't be
an enabler, you know, you give them the harshness that they need
in order to get their path their life back on path on
the right path. ואמר רבי אלעזר, V'amar Rabbi Elazar, כל אדם שאין
בו דעה, kol adam she'ein bo de'ah, לסוף גולה, lesof goleh, in
the end will be exiled. שנאמר, she'ne'emar, לכן גלה עמי מבלי דעת,
lachen gala ami mibli da'at, because of lack of knowledge. So, you
know, you will you will lose your, you know, what you have.
Or is this just a manifestation of the classic rabbinic antipathy towards
עם הארץ? am ha'aretz?
Maybe, although it doesn't sound like it's specifically עם הארץ am ha'aretz
directed. ואמר, V'amar, I mean, this, עם הארץ am ha'aretz weren't people
that weren't intelligent, right? They were people that were that were involved
in like being farmers and not in being תלמידי חכמים. talmidei chachamim.
ואמר רבי אלעזר, V'amar Rabbi Elazar, כל בית שאין דברי תורה נשמעין
בו בלילה, kol bayit she'ein divrei Torah nishma'in bo balaylah, I mean
right, not the way we use
עם הארץ. am ha'aretz. Any house that Torah's not heard at night,
אש אוכלתו, esh ochalto, a fire should consume it. שנאמר, she'ne'emar, כל
חושך טמון לצפוניו, kol choshech tamun litzfunav, darkness is hidden for the
צפוניו, tzfunav, the צפון, tzafun, you know, when when the צפון tzafun
could refer here to תורה, Torah you know, when you sort of,
you know, when the תורה Torah, is hidden in the time of
darkness, so תאכלהו אש לא נפח, tochalehu esh lo nupach, then a
fire that does not require blowing, you know, like the fire of
גיהינום gehinom will consume it. ירע שריד באוהלו, yera sarid be'ohalo,
שריד sarid is evil in the tent. ואין שריד אלא תלמידי חכמים,
ve'ein sarid ela talmidei chachamim, and it means that you don't want
תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim in your tent. שנאמר, she'ne'emar, ובשרידים אשר ה'
קורא, u'vaseridim asher Hashem koreh, by the remnant that God calls out.
Now, this by the way I feel is very powerful because, you
know, what's the importance of night? So the מהרש"א Maharsha says because
at night basically, you know, everything is like quiet and you have
don't have any distractions and you can't say, you know, you have
to be working on the farm, etc. Okay, and at that at
that time, you know, that's often I'd say, you know, I say
this point I sometimes make is that people's your character sometimes is
shown by how what you do with your, you know, your night
leisure time discretionary time, right? Like when you don't have any other
things to do, what do you do? Right, you know, do you
do like we were saying before, do you open up some book
that's, you know, develops your mind or do you open up a
junk novel? Do you learn תורה, Torah do you watch TV? Right.
So if you there's no תורה Torah at the night, if there's
no תורה Torah in the day we understand, people have to earn
a living. But if there's no תורה Torah. at night, then it's
shown that you're really don't have any interest in terms of learning
תורה. Torah, All right, and ואמר רבי אלעזר,
V'amar Rabbi
Elazar, כל שאינו משייר פת על שולחנו, kol she'eino meshayer pat al
shulchano, anybody who does not leave bread on their table, אינו רואה
סימן ברכה לעולם, eino ro'eh siman bracha le'olam, does not see a
סימן ברכה siman bracha because it's a way of what? Did I
skip something? Did I skip something? ואמר רבי
אלעזר, V'amar Rabbi Elazar, כל שאינו... Oh, I did skip. ואמר רבי
אלעזר, V'amar Rabbi Elazar, כל שאינו מהנה תלמידי חכמים מנכסיו. kol she'eino
mehaneh talmidei chachamim minchasav. So the way מהרש"א Maharsha says is let's
say you're not able to learn תורה, Torah. you just don't have
the mind for it. Fine. But you can support people who learn
תורה. Torah And if you anybody who doesn't support people who learn
תורה Torah, from their property, if they're spending their time earning money
and they're they can't really learn תורה, Torah! אינו רואה... but so
fine at least support תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim and if you don't,
אינו רואה סימן ברכה לעולם, eino ro'eh siman bracha le'olam, you don't,
שנאמר, she'ne'emar, אין שריד לאכלו על כן לא יחיל טובו. ein sarid
le'ochlo al ken lo yachil tuvo. ואין שריד אלא תלמידי חכמים, ve'ein
sarid ela talmidei chachamim, so if
there is no שריד, sarid, if תלמידי חכמים don't benefit from your
goodness, then you will not see any good. שנאמר, she'ne'emar, ובשרידים אשר
ה' קורא. u'vaseridim asher Hashem koreh. ואמר רבי אלעזר, V'amar Rabbi Elazar,
כל שאינו משייר פת על שולחנו, kol she'eino meshayer pat al shulchano,
if you don't leave a little bread on your table. ואמר רב
אלעזר, V'amar Rav Elazar, כל שאינו משייר פת על שולחן, kol sheino
meshayer pas al shulchan, if you don't leave a little bread on
your table, אין רואה סימן ברכה לעולם, ein roeh siman bracha l'olam,
because that sort of shows that God, אכלנו והותר, achalnu v'hoteir, God
gave us so much and that we even have some left over,
שנאמר, shene'emar, אין שריד לאכלו על כן לא יחיל טובו. ein sarid
l'achlo al kein lo yachil tuvo. Okay, if you don't leave over
anything, you cannot look forward to any goodness. I think the מהרש"א
Maharsha might also say that if you leave over crumbs then you
allow the poor to come in afterwards and eat from the crumbs.
Leftovers is חיוב מן התורה. chiyuv min hatorah. What? Leftovers.
ואמר רבי אלעזר, V'amar Rabbi Elazar, כל המשייר פתיתים על שולחנו כאילו
עובד עבודה זרה? kol hamishayer p'tisim al shulchano k'ilu oved avoda zara?
Doesn't the same רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar say if you leave crumbs
on your table it's like you're doing עבודה זרה? avoda zara? שנאמר,
Shene'emar, העורכים לגד שולחן והממלאים למני ממסך, ha'orchim la'gad shulchan v'hamemalim limni
mimsach, those that set for the גד, gad, not G-O-D, anyway גד
gad is a type of עבודה זרה, avoda zara, their table was
a way of worshipping this עבודה זרה avoda zara by like laying
out a table for it and you fill up, you know, the
vessels with libations. So it's a type of עבודה זרה. avoda zara.
לא קשיא. הא דאיכא שלימה בהדיה, Ha de'ika sheleima bahadeih, if you
put a whole loaf of bread together with it, that's a type
of an עבודה זרה avoda zara ritual. הא דליכא שלימה בהדיה, Ha
de'leika sheleima bahadeih, if you don't put a whole loaf of bread,
you just leave a little crumbs, then that is showing your sense
that God has given you more than you need and so on.
ואמר רבי אלעזר, V'amar Rabbi Elazar, רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar also said,
כל המחליף בדיבורו כאילו עובד עבודה זרה. kol hamachlif bediburo k'ilu oved
avoda zara. And anybody who changes their words and you could mean
that means like you first said one thing and then you didn't
keep a promise or you changed your mind. Now what's so bad
about changing your mind, you know? But okay, but maybe one would
say מחליף machlif means you don't keep a promise. But what's going
to look from the context is, it means no, you misrepresent yourself.
You say one thing but that's not, you know, from the very
beginning where we're saying something which is not your intention. Okay, כאילו
עובד עבודה זרה. k'ilu oved avoda zara. כתיב הכא והייתי בעיניו כמתעתע,
Ktiv hacha v'hayisi be'einei kimsata'teia, right that's by יעקב Yaakov and עשו,
Esav, I will be in my father's eyes like a whatever, deceiver
I guess, okay, but that's so but again that's exactly saying something
that at the time is not true. וכתיב התם הבל המה מעשה
תעתועים. U'ktiv hatam hevel heima ma'aseh tatu'im. They are nothingness, they are
all deception, right? Because עבודה זרה avoda zara itself is like an
illusion and a deception and so on. ואמר רבי אלעזר, V'amar Rabbi
Elazar, כל המסתכל בערוה קשתו ננערת. kol hamistakel be'erva kashto ninarat.
Anybody who looks at an ערוה. erva. Now רש"י Rashi says this
means one of two possibilities, either obviously talking about man and looks
at, you know, a woman's genitals, okay, or it just means somebody
who's constantly thinking, the one that רש"י Rashi prefers is a man
who's constantly thinking about sinning in a type of a sexual
thing. המסתכל? Hamistakel? I know, מסתכל mistakel suggests more the first one.
Anyway, his punishment is that his bow is shaken out, which basically
means he loses his ability to have an erection.
He loses his virility.
Impotent,
right, right. Okay, שנאמר, shene'emar, עריה תעור קשתך. aryeh teior kashtecha. Okay
so עריה aryeh is read as ערוה, erva, fine.
ואמר רבי אלעזר, לעולם הוי קבל וקיים. le'olam hvei kavel v'kayam. You
should always be sort of, מהרש"א Maharsha says this means either either
means like submissive or accepting or dark or מהרש"א Maharsha points out
that the word קבל kavel in Aramaic means dark, but like like
don't go ahead and be a complainer or don't go ahead and
sort of publicize your success, just accept things and you will therefore
survive. שנאמר, Shene'emar,
אמר רבי זירא, amar Rabbi Zeira, אף אנן נמי תנינא. af anan
nami tanina. We taught similarly. בית אפל אין פותחין לו חלונות לראות
נגעו. Bayis hafel ein potchin lo chalonos liros nigo. A dark house,
you know, if it says כנגד נראה לי בבית. kineged niru li
babayis. So if the house doesn't have enough light, you don't bring
in light into the house in order to see the spots. So
if you keep yourself quiet and humble or whatever, you know, then
you're not asking your own imperfections, your own נגעים nega'im sort of,
you know, for people to be to see them and to critique
them or whatever. So stay in the background. Okay, שמע מינה. shma
mina.
אמר רבי טבי אמר רבי יאשיה, Amar Rabbi Tavi amar Rabbi Yoshiya,
מאי דכתיב, mai dichativ, what's meant by the פסוק, pasuk, שאול ועוצר
רחם ארץ לא שבעה מים. She'ol v'otzer rachem eretz lo save'ah mayim.
So these three things are never satisfied. The depths, meaning the depths
of like presumably גיהנום, Gehennom, type of depths, right, and the womb,
and a land that always needs water. וכי מה ענין שאול אצל
רחם. V'chi ma inyan She'ol etzel rachem. So I get, says the
גמרא, that's the way the מהרש"א Maharsha reads it, why a land
that always needs water never gets enough water, but what's the comparison
of the depths and גיהנום Gehennom to the womb? Okay.
אלא לומר לך, Ela lomar lecha, to tell you, מה רחם מכניס
ומוציא, ma rachem machnis u'motzi, the same way a womb brings in
and brings out, it brings in when the semen enters it brings
out when the child is born, אף שאול מכניס ומוציא, af She'ol
machnis u'motzi, the depths, the underworld, that's probably a better translation,
souls go in and then they'll come out. So this is another
proof of תחיית המתים.
techiyas hameisim In a roundabout way though, right?
I know. והלא דבר קל וחומר, ve'lo d'var kal vachomer, it's a
קל וחומר, kal vachomer, מה רחם שמכניסין לו בחשאי, ma rachem shemachnisin
lo bechashai, when the stuff goes in it's in private, right, the
couple's it's intimate nobody else is around, מוציאין ממנו בקולי קולות, motzi'in
mimeno be'kolei kolos, when the baby is born the baby is screaming
and everybody knows about it. שאול שמכניסין בו בקולי קולות, She'ol shemachnisin
bo be'kolei kolos, when somebody is brought down into the underworld meaning
at a funeral. Right, a big whole procession everybody knows about it.
אינו דין שמוציאין ממנו בקולי קולות? eino din shemotzi'in mimeno bekolei kolos?
How much more so when the soul comes out, it'll be, you
know, publicized and it'll be a tremendous miracle. מכאן תחיית המתים מן
התורה, mikan techiyas hameisim min hatorah, if you were wondering where it
was going. Okay, תנא דבי אליהו, tana d'bei Eliyahu, we talked from
the דבי אליהו. d'bei Eliyahu. צדיקים שעתיד הקדוש ברוך הוא להחיותן אינן
חוזרין לעפרם. tzadikkim she'asid Hakadosh Baruch Hu lehachayosan einan chozrin la'afaram. Now
we get to this question: after תחיית המתים, techiyas hameisim... what's going
to happen to them, right? So are people going to then live
forever, is there going to be this period then that's going to
lead to an עולם הבא period, people will live forever, etc.? We
sort of said before, people will live forever, here we're saying it.
Okay, but you could have imagined, maybe there's a תחיית המתים, techiyas
hameisim, we live for a few hundred years in a Messianic period,
maybe an עולם הבא comes afterwards, right? But this is saying no,
the צדיקים tzadikkim that are resurrected will not die again. Okay, אינם
חוזרין לעפרם, einam chozrin la'afaram, will not go back to their dust.
שנאמר והיה הנשאר בציון והנותר בירושלים קדוש יאמר לו כל הכתוב לחיים
בירושלים. shene'emar ve'haya hanishar beTzion vehanosar biYrushalayim kadosh ye'amer lo kol hakasuv
lachayim biYrushalayim. There
we said holy, everybody that is written for life. מה קודש לעולם
קיים, mah kodesh le'olam kayam, the same way what is holy is
always around. What does that mean? I mean the בית המקדש, beis
hamikdash, you know, what does that
mean מה קודש לעולם קיים mah kodesh le'olam kayam means? But anyway,
אף הם לעולם קיימין, af heim le'olam kayamin, they are always around.
ואם תאמר, ve'im tomar, and if you say or just get a
little bit further here, ואם תאמר אותן שנים שעשה הקדוש ברוך הוא
לחדש בהן
את עולמו, ve'im tomar osan shanim she'asa Hakadosh Baruch Hu lechadesh bahen
es olamo, one minute! But how about the fact that there will
be a period between תחיית המתים techiyas hameisim and עולם הבא? How
are they going to live? And now we're going to get to
a new idea that between the תחיית המתים...
techiyas hameisim,
okay, so there's going to be a תחיית המתים, techiyas hameisim. there's
going to be a יום הדין yom hadin where the צדיקים tzadikkim
will where oh sort
of live and the רשעים rasha'im were going to גיהנום. Gehenom.
Okay, and then there'll be an עולם הבא where we basically said
people will like, I don't know, you know, אין אכילה ואין
שתייה
ein achila ve'ein
shtiya and whatever יושבים ועטרותיהם בראשיהם, yoshvim ve'atroteihem berosheihem, before we also
said they'll live forever. Okay. So how long is this period going
to be of Messianic period, and what's going to happen to transition
between this period and this period? So now the גמרא is going
to say that there was going to be a thousand years where
the world was going to be destroyed and God is going to
be working at creating the new world, okay, like a בריאת העולם.
bri'as ha'olam. Okay, so if these צדיקים tzadikkim that were resurrected here
are going to live forever, what are they going to do in
the intervening thousand years? All right, so אותן שנים שעשה הקדוש ברוך
הוא לחדש בהן את עולמו, osan shanim she'asa Hakadosh Baruch Hu lechadesh
bahen es olamo, when God is remakes the world, שנאמר ונשגב ה'
לבדו ביום ההוא, shene'emar venisgav Hashem levado bayom hahu, God will be
alone at that time, צדיקים מה עושין? tzadikkim mah osin? What are
the צדיקים tzadikkim going to be? הקדוש ברוך הוא עושה להם כנפיים
כנשרים. Hakadosh Baruch Hu oseh lahem knafayim kenesharim. Oh, God will give
them wings like eagles or like ravens, לשוט על פני המים, lashat
al pnei hamayim, and they'll just hover like quoting the פסוק, pasuk
right, of ורוח אלהים מרחפת על פני המים. ve'ruach elokim merachefes al
pnei hamayim. It's obviously echoing that. So the spirit of the צדיקים
tzadikkim or the bodies because we're saying it's actually would be their
bodies will survive, their bodies will be hovering over the water, will
be going back to that בראשית bereishis period where it'll just be
the world be תוהו ובוהו tohu vavohu and water, but the bodies
of the צדיקים will be flying like eagles and hovering over the
water. שנאמר על כן לא נירא בהמיר ארץ, shene'emar al kein lo
nira behamir aretz, we will not fear when the land is changed,
במוט הרים בלב ימים. bemot harim belev yamim. Okay, because ושמא תאמר
יש להם צער, ve'shema tomar yesh lahem tza'ar, maybe it'll be painful
for them. תלמוד לומר וקווי ה' יחליפו כח, talmud lomar vekoyei Hashem
yachalifu koach, those that believe in God will be given new strength,
יעלו אבר כנשרים, ya'alu ever kenesharim, they will get wings like eagles,
ירוצו ולא ייגעו, yarutzu velo yiga'u, they will run and will not
weary, ילכו ולא ייעפו, yelchu velo yif'u, and they go and they
will not tire. Okay, so now so that's what'll happen, that's we
got this whole thing worked out. Now let's just do a little
bit more because what's-his-name Michal is going to take over, so if
you give me like a few more minutes I'll just try to
get a little
further. The גמרא says ונילף ממתים שהחיה יחזקאל, venilef mimeisim she'hechiya Yechezkel,
here you go David. The way the מהרש"א Marsha reads this is:
why not learn out תחיית המתים from the whole יחזקאל Yechezkel story?
Why do we have to go to all these other things? יחזקאל
Yechezkel brought them to life. And even if that doesn't prove that
there'll be תחיית המתים, let's say in the future world, at least
it proves that it's possible for God to do a תחיית המתים.
Part of the whole challenge is: how can God turn dirt back
into a human being? So what do you mean? You have the
miracle written in the תורה! He brought them back to life. Okay,
which is different by the way than אלישע, Elisha, because אלישע Elisha
brought somebody who had just died back to life. But יחזקאל Yechezkel
brought dirt back to life, old bones back to life. So why
isn't that a basis to show that God can do it, that
it can happen? סבר לה כמאן דאמר באמת משל היה. savar lah
keman de'amar be'emes mashal haya. No, it's of the opinion that said
that this was actually a משל. mashal. It's a very interesting phrase:
in truth, it was just a משל. mashal. Okay, so therefore you
can't prove anything from it. The משל mashal was, like the פסוק
says, כל בית ישראל המה, kol beis Yisrael heima, they all are
this is the Jewish people, they think that you know, our hope
is lost, we're dead, etc. No, you'll be brought back to life.
So it was all a metaphor. Now could have been both a
miracle... And the metaphor, but this is saying it was just a
metaphor. It never actually happened. דתניא *De-tanya*, we taught in a ברייתא
*brayta*, רבי אליעזר אומר מתים שהחיה יחזקאל עמדו על רגליהם ואמרו שירה
*Rebbe Eliezer omer meisim shehechya yechezkel amdu al ragleihem va-amru shirah*. It
actually happened. They stood up and they sang forth, ומתו *u-meisu*, and
then they died. Just but it's for the purpose of the lesson.
מה שירה אמרו *mah shirah amru*, what שירה *shirah* did they say?
השם ממית בצדק ומחיה ברחמים *Hashem meimis be-tzedek u-mechayeh be-rachamim*. God caused
us to die with justice and gives us life ברחמים *be-rachamim* because
we didn't deserve it. רבי יהושע אומר שירה זו *Rebbe Yehoshua omer
shirah zu*, this שירה *shirah*. השם ממית ומחיה מוריד שאול ויעל *Hashem
meimis u-mechayeh morid sheol va-ya’al*. Right, he brings down to the depths,
the underworld, and brought us back up, which is again this soul
that the soul rises back up as well. רבי יהודה אומר אמת
משל היה *Rebbe Yehuda omer emes mashal haya*. אמר ליה רבי נחמיה
אם אמת למה משל ואם משל למה אמת *Amar lei Rebbe Nechemiah
im emes lama mashal ve-im mashal lama emes*. What do you mean
in truth it was a משל *mashal*? Either it’s true or it
was a משל *mashal*. אלא באמת משל היה *Ela be-emes mashal haya*.
In truth it was really just a משל *mashal*. רבי אליעזר בנו
של רבי יוסי הגלילי אומר מתים שהחיה יחזקאל עלו לארץ ישראל ונשאו
נשים *Rebbe Eliezer beno shel Rebbe Yose HaGlili omer meisim shehechya yechezkel
alu le-Eretz Yisrael ve-nasu nashim*. They actually, they made עליה *aliyah* because
the whole metaphor was like you’ll ultimately leave the exile and go
back to the land, and they married women, והולידו בנים ובנות *va-olidu
banim u-vanot*, and they had children. עמד רבי יהודה בן בתירה על
רגליו ואמר אני מבני בניהם והלו תפילין שהניח לי אבי אבי מהם
*Amad Rebbe Yehuda ben Beseira al raglav ve-amar ani mibnei beneihem ve-halu
tefillin she-hiniach li avi avi me-hem*. And I have the תפילין *tefillin*
that I inherited from them. Okay, ומן הם מתים שהחיה יחזקאל *u-man
heim meisim she-hechya yechezkel*? Now who were these dead? אמר רב אלו
בני אפרים שמנו לקץ וטעו *Amar Rav elu benei Ephraim she-manu la-keitz
ve-ta’u*. These are the בני אפרים *benei Ephraim* that they tried to
anticipate when the when the ultimate redemption would be and they left
Egypt too early and they were wiped out. And so therefore they
were resurrected. Maybe there’s also a subtle message here that we’re talking
all this stuff about Messianic times, don’t try to be too much
to try to anticipate when it’s going to be. שנאמר ובני אפרים
שותלח וברד בנו ותחת בנו ואלעדה בנו ותחת בנו וזבד בנו ושותלח
בנו ועזר ואלעד והרגום אנשי גת *she-ne'emar u-venei Ephraim Shuthelach ve-bered beno
ve-tachath beno ve-eladah beno ve-tachath beno ve-zavad beno ve-shuthelach beno ve-ezer ve-elad
va-haragum anshei Gat*. Okay, so these children of אפרים *Ephraim* were killed
by the people of גת *Gat*, הנולדים בארץ *ha-noladim ba-aretz* that were
born in the land, in Israel. So how did they get to
Israel, these בני אפרים *benei Ephraim*, and they were killed? It must
be they tried, they pushed the Exodus too soon. וכתיב ויתאבל אפרים
אביהם ימים רבים ויבאו אחיו לנחמו *Ve-kasiv vayisabel Ephraim avihem yamim rabbim
va-yavo'u echav le-nachamo*. Okay. ושמואל אמר אלו בני אדם שכפרו בתחיית המתים
*Ve-Shmuel amar elu benei adam she-kafru bi-tchiyas ha-meisim*. These are people that
denied resurrection. So all you people out there, we’ve been trying to
prove to you for the last two דפים *dapim* that there’s תחיית
המתים *tchiyas ha-meisim*. Okay, so here you see that they were punished,
that they died. So now if they died, why do they get
resurrected? The whole point is if you deny, you don’t get resurrected.
But it was to prove a point to them. Okay, שנאמר ויאמר
אלי בן אדם העצמות האלה כל בית ישראל המה הנה אומרים יבשו
עצמותינו ואבדה תקותנו נגזרנו לנו *she-ne’emar va-yomer elai ben adam ha-atzamot ha-eleh
kol beis Yisrael heimah hineh omrim yavshu atzmosenu ve-avda tikvasenu nigzarnu lanu*.
Our bones are dried up, meaning these are the people that didn’t
believe in תחיית המתים *tchiyas ha-meisim*. I will use their bones to
show them, you know, that there is תחיית המתים *tchiyas ha-meisim*. So
the whole point was to prove תחיית המתים *tchiyas ha-meisim*. רבי ירמיה
בר אבא אמר אלו בני אדם שאין בהם לחלוחית של מצוה *Rebbe
Yirmiyah bar Abba amar elu benei adam she-ein bahem lachluchis shel mitzvah*.
These are people that don’t even have any moisture, they’re totally dried.
They don’t even have any מצוות *mitzvot*. They don’t deserve to be
resurrected at all. Okay, שנאמר העצמות היבשות שמעו דבר השם *she-ne’emar ha-atzamot
hayeveshos shim’u devar Hashem*. And nevertheless, it shows that God will, you
know, maybe it’s saying that even those without מצוות *mitzvot* will be
resurrected. כל ישראל יש להם חלק לעולם הבא *Kol Yisrael yesh lahem
chelek le-olam haba*, or maybe they’ll be resurrected to stand for יום
הדין *yom hadin*. Okay. רבי יצחק נפחא אמר אלו בני אדם שחיפו
את ההיכל כולו שקצים ורמשים *Rebbe Yitzchak Nafcha amar elu benei adam
she-chippu es ha-heichal kulo shekatzim u-remasim*. These are the people that covered
the sanctuary, the Temple, with images of these like, you know, whatever,
rodents and vermin. שנאמר ואבוא ואראה והנה כל תבנית רמש ובהמה שקץ
וכל גילולי בית ישראל מחקה על הקיר סביב סביב *She-ne’emar va-avo va-ereh
vehineh kol tavnis remes u-veheimah sheketz ve-chol gillulei beis Yisrael mechukkah al
hakir saviv saviv*. And they, they engraved these types of images all
on the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*. וכתיב התם והעבירני עליהם סביב סביב
*U-chsiv hasam ve-he'everani aleihem saviv saviv*.
The comparison of the word סביב סביב *saviv saviv* around, around. So
these were the people that did this terrible sin. It's a little
ironic. They did this terrible sin and now they're being resurrected. But
maybe they're being resurrected to show like, you know, you guys, you
blew it because if you, you know, had done מצוות *mitzvos*, you'd
be resurrected and you'd live. Now you're being, you know, maybe you
were denying the ability of resurrection, you're now seeing what you missed
out on. רבי יוחנן אמר *Rebbe Yochanan amar* just one more line
here, אלו מתים שבבקעת דורא *elu meisim she-be-vikas Dura*. Those are the
those that died in the valley of Dura. Who are those? ואמר
רבי יוחנן מנהר אשל עד רבת בקעת דורא Bikas Dura. *Ve-amar Rebbe
Yochanan mi-nhar Eshel ad ravath bikas Dura* from this place from this
place to the valley of Dura, שבשעה שהגלה נבוכדנצר רשע rasha את
ישראל *she-be-vasha she-higlah Nevuchadnetzar rasha es Yisrael*, when Nevuchadnetzar exiled the Jewish
people, היו בהם בחורים שהיו מגנין את החמה ביופיין *hayu vahem bachurim
she-hayu meganin es hachamah be-yofyan*.
There were people, there were young men that were so beautiful, the
sun was, you know, they made the sun, you know, look ugly
because they were so beautiful. והיו כשדיות *Ve-hayu Kasdiyos*, and the Chaldeans,
רואין אותן ושופצות זבות *ro'in osan ve-shofzos zavos*. The Chaldean women saw
them and they were and they, you know, they bled out of
desire. The גמרא *Gemara* believes that the same way a man, you
know, sees semen out of sexual desire, a woman could bleed out
of sexual desire. אמרו לבעליהן *Amru le-va'aleihen*, they said to their husbands,
oh my god, there's these gorgeous men. ובעליהן למלך *U-va'aleihen la-melech*, the
husbands told the king. צוה המלך והרגום *Tzivah ha-melech va-haragum*, so the
king wiped them out. Like the guys didn’t want their women lusting
after. And therefore they were resurrected
because they died unjustly. תנו רבנן בשעה שהפיל נבוכדנצר הרשע את חנניה
מישאל ועזריה לכבשן האש besha'ah she'hipil Nevuchadnezzar harasha et Chananya Mishael va'Azarya
l'kivshan ha'esh
when he threw Hananiah, Mishael, and Azariah into the fire, אמר לו
הקדוש ברוך הוא ליחזקאל amar lo hakadosh baruch hu l'Yechezkel לך והחיי
מתים
בבקעת דורא lech v'hachaye meitim be'Bikas Dura go resurrect the dead in
בקעת
דורא. Bikas Dura כיון שהחיה אותן keivan she'hechya osan he resurrected them,
באו עצמות וטפחו לו לאותו רשע על פניו ba'u atzamot v'tapchu lo
l'oso rasha al panav so they they walked back into Nebuchadnezzar's where
he was getting ready to throw חנניה Chananya מישאל Mishael and עזריה
Azarya into the כבשן האש kivshan ha'esh and they hit him on
his head, okay, they slapped him on his head. אמרו מה טיבן
של אלו amru ma tivan shel elu so he said, who who
are these people that walked into my castle and hit me on
the head? אמרו לו חבריהן של אלו מחיה מתים בבקעת
דורא amru lo chavreihen shel elu mechayei meitim be'Bikas Dura the friends
of these חנניה Chananya מישאל Mishael and עזריה's Azarya friends,
meaning Ezekiel presumably who was their friend, he went and he resurrected
the dead in בקעת דורא that you killed out. And now you're
about to throw them, חנניה Chananya מישאל ועזריה Mishael va'Azarya into the
כבשן האש kivshan ha'esh it probably will not end well. Okay. פתח
ואמר patach v'amar so he opened and he said, אתוהי כמה רברבין
atvohi kama ravrevin God's miracles how great they are, ותמהוהי כמה תקיפין
v'timhohi kama takiffin how wonderful are God's miracles, מלכותה מלכות עלם ושלטנה
עם דר ודר malchuteh malchut alam v'shaltaneh im dar v'dar his
his kingdom is forever, his ruling is forever. Okay. אמר רבי יצחק
amar Rabbi Yitzchak יוצק זהב רותח לתוך פיו של אותו רשע yutzak
zahav roteach l'toch piv shel oto rasha gold molten gold should be
poured down to that רשע rasha person Nebuchadnezzar שאילמלא בא מלאך וסטרו
על פניו she'ilmale ba malach u'staro al panav the angel came and
slapped him on his face when he was starting to praise God,
בקש לגנות כל שירות ותשבחות שאמר דוד בספר תהלים bikeish l'ganot kol
shirot v'tishbachot she'amar David b'sefer Tehillim he would have sang God's praises
and would have embarrassed, you know, David's praises in תהלים Tehillim so
now he was such a רשע he didn't deserve that opportunity, okay,
but here he was, he recognized God's greatness because of these that
people that were resurrected. I think we can end there. Thank you
for giving me that extra time, we pretty much got all caught
up. Okay. יישר כח. yashar koach.